DAN KLEIN: All right.
Now let's talk about an important
algorithm called policy iteration,
which combines the idea of evaluating
one policy with the idea of improving
that policy on the basis
of those values.
You can think of policy iteration as
you've got a policy in front of you,
and you're constantly trying
to make it better.
So let's think about y value iteration
as not always the best solution.
Well, what value iteration
does is essentially
mimics the Bellman updates.
You have iterations where k gets larger
and larger, starting at zero.
And for each iteration,
you visit each state.
And for each state, you
look at each action.
And for each action, you
look at each outcome.
One problem with that process
is it's slow.
And the reason it's slow is each
iteration not only looks at every
source and target state, and so is s
squared, it also has to consider each
action each time.
And there are often many actions.
Another problem is that although
you're considering all of these
actions, the maximum often
doesn't change.
Let's see a demo of that.
So here is a grid.
This is sum setting of grid world.
And let's watch what happens.
At v0, all the values are going
to be zero because there is
0 time steps left.
At v1, you can see one
step into the future.
If you're at an exit, you
get the exit value.
If you're anywhere else, you get just
the living reward, which in this case
is minus 0.1.
If I look further into the future, we
know that in value iteration, the
rewards from that plus 1 are
going to propagate out.
This is nine iterations in.
If I run it to convergence,
things keep changing.
Why is that?
That's because there are very long
sequences that still give you points
from that plus 1, that take a while
to register in the lower left.
But let's look a little more closely.
What I want you to watch this time is I
want you to watch as I increase k in
value iteration.
I want you to watch the arrows.
And we're going to this twice.
First I want you to watch
them changing.
So at the beginning, they're
going to change a lot.
But eventually, they stop changing.
And then even when I run into 100,
they still haven't changed since
iteration eight or nine.
Secondly, watch in kind
of the lower left.
These numbers are changing, but it takes
a while before the change is to
become large enough that they
impact one of the arrows.
So now we're in a position
where we can see these
problems with value iteration.
Each iteration is slow because it
considers all of the actions.
But that maximum, that best action that
you got when you considered them
all usually doesn't change.
So you wasted all that time, if you have
100 actions, checking the other
99 that weren't very good last round.
They're still not very good, but
you still check them all.
In addition, as we saw in that example,
the policy may be converged
when the values are nowhere
near converged yet.
So the policy tends to finish long
before the values converge.
So what can we do?
The idea here is an algorithm called
policy iteration, which is an
alternative approach.
And the basic sketch is we're going to
have two steps that we alternate.
Step one is policy evaluation.
We're going to have some fixed policy.
It's generally not going to be an
optimal policy, but we're going to
figure out its values using
policy evaluation.
Which if we remember, was fast because
it didn't have that factor of a.
So we evaluate the policy we
have, even though it's
not an optimal policy.
Then we take those values, and we
extract a better policy from them.
That's called policy improvement.
And the way we do policy improvement is
we extract the policy implied by a
one step look ahead from those values
we just computed in step one.
We repeat these until the policy
converges, and it turns out you're
guaranteed that the policy
will always keep getting
better, and then converge.
This algorithm is policy iteration.
It's still optimal, and it can converge
much faster under some
conditions.
The conditions under which it converges
much faster tend to be ones
where there are a large number of
actions, but where the maximizing
action doesn't change very much
during value iteration rounds.
If we wrote this out in equations, it
would look something like this.
Step one is evaluation, so I fix
some policy, pi, and I'm going
to compute v pi.
That is we asked before why would
we want to compute the
values for a fixed policy?
Here's a case.
I fixed pi, and I compute the values.
And so I do this modified, or simplified
update where I don't max
over the actions.
I assume that my policy pi is fixed,
and I only do the averaging at the
chance nodes.
So this thing is fast, because I
don't consider all the actions.
Once this thing converges, or gets close
enough, I then stop and I say,
let's give the actions a chance to
change, because we've done enough of
this evaluation that maybe by now, some
of the actions need to change.
So again, we're going to do a one step
look ahead, and just unroll that
expectimax one layer, and say the new
policy is the action that I would get
if I did a one step expectimax.
And then plugged in the values, not
optimal values, but the values
computed against my old policy.
That's a little weird, right?
We do one step of actual expectimax,
and our truncation
function is our old policy.
Now, why should that be better?
Well, maybe the policy was good, or
maybe the old policy was bad.
But whatever it was, good or bad,
we've just pushed it one
step into the future.
And that step where we did that one
layer of expectimax, that layer,
insofar as a layer can be optimal,
did the optimal computation.
So we've got one layer of real optimal
expectimax, and then the truncation
function is the old values.
And every time we do this, we push the
old stuff farther and farther into the
future, and thereby make progress.
If you think about this, it actually
turns out the improvement step is just
like value iteration.
We loop over all the actions, and for
each action, we loop over all of the
results s prime.
So the improvement step isn't going
to be particularly fast.
It's essentially the evaluation
step where we get a big speed
up over value iteration.
And because the evaluation step happens
many times before we allow an
improvement step, we
get a big speed up.
Another way of looking at this algorithm
is thinking that we're doing
value iteration, but on most rounds we
just go with the last action that
optimized for the state, rather
than considering them all.
OK, let's compare them.
Both value iteration and policy
iteration do the same thing.
You input an MDP, and what is output
is an optimal quantity.
And on the surface that's the optimal
values, but they both also provide
optimal policies.
In the case of policy iteration,
it explicitly provides that.
In the case of value iteration, you
just keep track of it as you go.
So they both compute optimal values.
In value iteration, every iteration
updates the values and implicitly by
doing this max every time, the policy.
In policy iteration, we do lots of
passes that only update the utilities,
the values for this fixed policy.
Only when we do a policy improvement
step do we allow the policy to change,
and because of that,
it's often faster.
Both of them of the same
class of thing.
They are both dynamic programs which
take an MDP as input, and produce
optimal values and policies
as outputs.
We've got a lot of algorithms by now.
Even setting aside expectimax, which
was a way of choosing actions in an
MDP, we've still got a lot
of different things.
If you want to compute optimal values,
we've got value iteration, and we've
got policy iteration, which
do the same thing.
Policy iteration's a little more
complex, but it's often faster.
If all you wanted to do was compute
values for a particular policy, we
have policy evaluation.
If all you wanted to do was turn your
values into a policy, we have policy
extraction, which you can think of
as just a one step look ahead.
Depending on what you have as input, a
policy or not, and what you want as
output, optimal quantities or just the
evaluation of a single policy, that
determines what equations you use
and what algorithm you use.
And so you might be saying,
these all look the same.
That is a good reaction to have.
They basically are all the same.
These are all Bellman updates turned
into an iterative algorithm.
They all use a one step look
ahead expectimax fragment.
The difference is whether or not you
plug in a fixed policy, or actually do
a max over the actions.
That's it.
So once you really understand these
algorithms, you'll start feeling like,
oh, it's all just Bellman equations and
the corresponding dynamic program.
And that's a great place to be.